let's now look at the solution for our
nbit history predictor quiz we said that
we want to have an nbit history
predictor with two bit counters per
possible history and we need 1,24
entries like that and now we want to
compute the cost for these predictors
how well they do on the NN NT pattern
and also how many of the two bit
counters do they actually use for the NT
repeating pattern the cost can be
computed as simply the size of the
history plus we need 2 to the nth 2bit
counters for each entry and if you
compute what this is it amounts to
532,250multifamily
234,00
1112 bits so this is many many megabits
worth of predictor stuff again for the
same number of entries as you can see
this is probably not a realistic
predictor at all and even this one
probably you don't want to spend that
much Hardware on just Branch prediction
let's now see how well they do on the NN
NT pattern this is a pattern of length
four so anything that has n equal three
or more will handle it well so from that
perspective all three of these will do
well these two will do well on even
longer patterns and finally how many of
those two bit counters that we have are
we actually using for the not taken
taken not taken taken think about it
this way for the N equals 1 when we need
to predict the taken Branch we have a
history of just zero because it's a
single bit history when we need to
predict the not Branch we have a history
of just one so we're using both of these
when we have n equal 4 and trying to
predict this not taken Branch our
history is 0 1 01 when we're trying to
predict the taken Branch the history
will be 1 1 0 when we're trying to
predict the next not taken Branch the
history again will be 0 1 01 so as you
can see really we will be only using
entries 0 1 01 and 1 0 1 0 so we're
still using only only
two of the 16 2bit counters if you look
at the 8bit history the history will
just be 0 1 0 1 0 1 01 and 1 0 1 0 1 0 1
0 here so we will still be using only
two of now
256 2bit counters so we are now using
less than 1% of the counters we have in
each entry and finally for this
history you can see the trend here we
will be using only two 2bit counters of
more than 65,000 that we have in each
entry